we're going to learn how you can
actually get the implied volatility over
historical data for 10 years using the
Theta data API now here we're also going
to explain what the difference is
between actual or realized volatility or
historical volatility to implied
volatility and how if you believe that
there's autocorrelation between these
two process this can actually help you
with your decision making in the future
or your understanding of volatility in
general we're going to be actually
exploring the implied volatility of at
the money options over historical 10
years of data for Microsoft so what is
the difference between historical
volatility and implied volatility well
let's start with historical volatility
historical volatility is the actual
variability in the stock price that
materializes over time through
Randomness now this Randomness is
formally described in mathematics as a
Winer process or Brownian motion and
we've actually created a video on what
this is in Finance before so if you're
interested check it out now essentially
there is a model that underlines this
price movement and here we assume that
the underlying model is geometric
Brownian motion and essentially what
that means is that when you take the
stock returns model you get something
that looks like this with log returns
now when we then calculate the
randomness in volatility over time
essentially you get that the realized
volatility is just the coefficient of
the Brownian motion term or that whiner
process term here so this happens under
the physical probability measure now if
you don't know what I'm talking about
here that's okay we can explain that in
a further video now here the realize
volatility over time we actually get the
sum over an entire period of time we get
the square root of the sum of the
squared log returns now if you wanted to
compute the realized volatility for each
each time period you're considering for
example on a daily basis or a five
minute basis then you would use the
unbiased standard deviation or the bias
standard deviation to then compute your
returns now why do you use the buyer
standard deviation well really sometimes
you can be dealing with a large volume
of data and many papers have shown that
there is an insignificant difference in
reality between these two methods but I
will leave that for your further
investigation to judge so essentially
this is the volatility that actually
transpires on a day-to-day basis now the
implied volatility on the other hand is
actually the implied volatility of how
the market is pricing the option
currently so what does this mean well to
calculate implied volatility you use the
market price of an option as well as all
the contract terms now there's also a
theoretical pricing model that's
actually dependent on a type of option
you're pricing for example if we're
pricing European in call options then we
might use the black shoals model
now the blackshells model looks like
this where you have the core price is
equal to the strike Times by The
cumulative normal distribution function
here we've got it as Phi with the
parameter D1 minus the strike the
expected discount
rate with the time to expiry multiplied
by the normal cumulative distribution
function with D2 now D1 and D2 are
defined below but essentially what this
means is that the implied volatility
that results is the observed market
price of the option so for a particular
option with a strike k and a time to
expiry Tau there will be an observable
market price so essentially you can take
that market price and that's the call
Price observed in the market for a
strike in town and you're going to then
find a value of the implied volatility
according to the model that then gives
you that same price so all other
parameters being equal you have the
strike you have today's stock price you
have the interest rate which hopefully
people agree on and then you can have
the tower so everything else being equal
if I just change the volatility what
volatility does that need to be to match
the market price at a particular strike
at a particular time to expiry so this
can be obtained by a number of methods
we won't get into them here I've made a
video on a route finding method at
Newton you can use bisection secant
Brent method and there are actually more
rational ways if you're doing this on
European options because it's a very
easy it's a very difficult easy problem
to solve if that makes sense so we're
going to get into a a more rational way
to compute this for European options in
future videos okay so you might say
that's all well and good but then what
is the actual difference between what
the Market's pricing it in and what the
historical volatility we're looking at
the math there but what's an intuitive
definition well since the mark Market
does not have perfect knowledge about
the Future these two numbers can and
will be different so Varian lies the
risk management problem for market
makers and institutions that have to
show
buy two-sided quotes and the actual
business or trading opportunity that's
present for hedge funds or other
institutions so I have partnered with
Theta data on this channel and the
reason I've done that is because I
believe in the power of this API so I am
enjoying using it and how much
information there is with 10 years of
historical data not just on end of day
information but intraday information on
both trades and quote level data that
wasn't even traded in that day we're
talking about hundreds and hundreds of
thousands of data points for each
particular option on each particular
trade date it's really incredible the
amount of data that this API offers so
Theta data API if you aren't interested
in actually purchasing a subscription to
this API and following along with the
tutorials that we're doing here then
essentially using my code in the
description Quant Pi when you go through
and purchase you will get 15 off for two
months additionally you're going to get
50 off your first month on top of that
so please take a look if you're
interested and I'm really enjoying the
product so far so let's import our
dependency so we've got OS time pickle
random numpy pandas matplotlib for
plotting date time time Delta date time
date and then from Theta data we're
importing Theta client option
requirement type option right date range
data type and stock requirement type so
first thing we're going to do is we're
going to use the API to get all
expirations for the Microsoft options so
let's see what they have available first
you need to Define your username and
password for the Theta data API have
this in my environmental variable
Bubbles and we Define a function called
get expirations essentially all I'm
doing is I'm enabling a Theta data
client I'm creating it I'm connecting to
the terminal and then I'm making a
request for a specific root ticker now
my root ticker that I'm looking at is
Microsoft and I get all the expirations
back so essentially here I get
561 different expiries all the way
starting from 2020 2012
June the first so that's over 10 years
of historical options data so getting
the strikes for each of these specific
option expiries now we need to build up
this dictionary and then we're going to
pickle this data down for later use so I
want the strikes for every single one of
those options so what do I have to do
let's create a function that says great
get strikes I'm going to create a faded
data client I'm going to then create a
dictionary called all strikes I'm going
to connect to the terminal and I'm going
to iterate through all my expiration
dates for a given route I'm going to
make the request and then I'm going to
add it to my dictionary so I'll return
that data as a pandas series and a
numeric series
so you can make that API request
and just call in that function with your
root ticker and expirations and then
I've pickled that data down for use now
and you can see that I've for all my
different expirations at different
points I can then return my ticker value
so that's very handy because obviously
they move with the underlying over time
now the Microsoft underline is very
important for actually getting the
historical volatility so let's actually
get the underline through a request to
Theta data so we're going to be
leveraging the ability to aggregate time
periods throughout the day using the API
and this is defined by the variable
interval size so we're going to be
comparing the historical volatility to
the implied volatility for every trading
day using the quotes level data that
were made in the underline in the
options at the money in the afternoon at
1400 so I've said a lot of things there
but essentially because of the
transparency and amount of data that
Theta data has we can actually get the
quote level data for every single day
every time point but that's too much so
we want to aggregate the data over a
given amount of time so let's say one
hour so I want the interval size to be
one hour and I'm going to get what
happened between 30 800 and 1400 every
day as a average of What the market
maker was quoting on that particular day
for both the underlying and for the
option price we're going to do this so
let's actually now request the
historical data for the underlying so
let's create the Theta data terminal
again we've got an underlying dictionary
that we're going to build up
connect to the terminal and then we're
going to iterate through the trading
dates
now for each trading date we go in to
try and get the data
so here we have to make the requirement
stock requirement type quote and then
we're going to list the date range which
is just going to be one day and we're
going to get the interval size which is
going to be uh one hourly period so then
I return the one hourly periods back and
then if you do the math we got 10
o'clock 11 o'clock uh 12 o'clock 13 and
then 1400 and then because python
indexes lists by from zero that is
number four so I'm getting all that data
back for a particular day and I'm only
interested in the 1400 time period so I
get that underlying back and I add it to
my dictionary if for some reason I can't
get a price for that particular day
because I'm not being very careful with
whether there was a particular holiday
back in 2012 I'm just doing business
days with my trading days I'm just going
to return a n a value now the way you
could get around that is you could be
more careful with describing your
historical period I was a little bit
lazy therefore I need to come up with
some exception handling now I want to
calculate the weighted mid price now
this is the micro price and all it means
is that I need to get the ask size and
the bid size along with this data very
easy to do
it it comes back from your response to
the Theta data API so I can apply this
uh this function here to my pandas array
and essentially all that I need to do is
just apply that function there so making
that actual request to the API
essentially you're just going to send it
off and you're going to return back
those values no problem so now we've
pickled that data the first thing we
want to do is we want to calculate
realized volatility now we want to do
this over a 30-day window but a 30-day
window and comparing it to implied
volatility is actually 21 trading days
ish in in actual trading days and the
reason is because a 30-day period from
from now to the future is only going to
have so many trading days business days
between now and then so I've computed
that I've approximated that as 21
trading days so what we're going to do
is we're going to calculate the realized
volatility so the cumulative realized
volatility oh over that window of time
so
the way that we can calculate realized
volatility is I've now got the subscript
H which is this rolling window period
and that's approximately the square root
of the sum of this return squared and
this return squared is the log price
difference
between the start of a period and the
end of a period given that the period
length changes depending on how we split
the 30 days or the 21 trading days up so
if I have M particular intervals then
this is my interval size and I step
through and I calculate the squared
returns and the sum of the squared
returns I take the square root of that
to get my realized volatility now
essentially what that means I can
essentially approximate this by using
the standard deviation over a rolling
trading window so let's see how I can
actually Implement that at code so how
do we actually implement this volatility
over the trading window in Python well
essentially let's make the data frame
using the underlying data we're going to
create a data frame of that information
we're going to then label the index as
the trade date we're then going to
calculate the log returns by taking
the log of One Price divided by the
shift of the other column and then we're
going to apply the trading days of 21 to
get our 30 days historical volatility
so let's create a new column called spot
Vol we're going to take the log returns
and we're going to take the dot rolling
function
with the window equal to the number of
trading days we then go into dot ST
which stands for standard deviation and
then we're going to take the square root
of 250 which is essentially using the
same formula that we saw before we get
in the summation over the we're getting
the standard deviations over a period of
time which is the uh the trading window
of 21 days and then we're then
multiplying by the frequency of every
year and this gives us our annual
rolling annualized 30-day
realized volatility so what does that
look like well essentially here is what
we've got we've got price for a
particular day and then we've got
volatility for a particular day the
30-day rolling average
so what does that look like well
essentially we can graph it and we get
something that looks like this I've got
price of Microsoft in blue running from
2012 Midway through all the way through
to today and then I have volatility in
percentage on the right hand side and
you can see uh the volatility change
over time in red now what I want to do
now is I want to get the implied
volatility so then we can plot it on top
of this so first thing we need to know
is that market makers are not forced to
show quotes on all options and this is
probably one of the biggest difficulties
that you'll ever have when using data
and trying to do historical analysis so
the rules are listed for each exchange
that the market makers must abide by and
essentially for the NASDAQ this can be
found here and I'll put a link in the
description
specifically there's a large difference
between competitive market makers and
what they have to do and primary market
makers on a particular option series now
the big difference is actually where the
market maker needs to actually show
two-sided quotes on non-standard options
like weeklies quarterly expiries or
adjusted options or not now standard
option prices we're going to be using
just to be safe to make sure that there
are quotes there these expire on the
Saturday following the third Friday of
every month and sometimes the expiry
date as the third Friday of the month so
in the past they seem to be recorded as
the Saturday and now they seem to be
recorded as on the third Friday of every
month so therefore we're going to take
the intersection of these two dates and
the expiries that we have with Theta
data which has all of them including the
weeklies the quarterlies and the
adjusted options and therefore we go
into then streamline it back to just
these standard options
so that we can more hopefully ensure
that we have quotes present in Market
making activity on these options series
so I'm going to get my trading date I'm
going to then calculate I will get a
pandas date range of the third Fridays
every month and then the Saturdays
following the third Fridays of every
month I'm going to combine the two and
then I'm going to check all the
expirations that I returned back from
Theta data and if they actually exist in
this combined list if they do then
return them if not then don't and look
I'm then going to get the number of
possible monthly options contracts which
is
essentially over calculated by two
because they took the Sunday and the
Saturday of every year but yeah 278
divided by 2 compared to the total
available 134 which it sounds right
about on that divided by two maybe a
little bit less and then we include the
quarterly and weekly options so the
total amount of options that data data
provides
563 so there are a lot of other options
obviously
so let's look at the days to expiry so
we're going to be interested in taking a
look at one month out two month out
three month out and four months out so
30 day 60 day 90 day and 120 days how
are we going to do that well essentially
we're going to run through for every
trading day what is the closest expiry
monthly expiry option that is closest to
30 days away 60 days away 90 days away
and 120 days away and the way we can do
that is we can use the difference
between these two date ranges so for a
particular trading day I'm going to
build up this dictionary contracts for a
particular trading day what is the
difference between all the list of
monthly expiries that I have
and the trade date and I'm going to get
the Delta of the days the number of days
and the difference then I'm going to run
through that list and I'm going to say
okay the Delta are the different days
what is the minimum for these particular
date to expiry times 30 days 60 days 90
days and 100 days and then I'm going to
return the index back for that and
essentially I'm just getting the index
position of that contract in the monthly
expiration list and I'm adding it to
this contract
contract dictionary so just for an
example what do I actually return well
then for every particular trading day I
return back four different index
positions for example the start is going
to be in this big list I want the first
four months of my trading data and for a
particular day in 2001 it looks like
this it's somewhere else in the array
that you're just going consecutive
months you want but you want to know
where they are so you can reference it
later now where are you going to
reference it later where you're going to
reference it later here in the implied
volatility request datadata uses quote
information on a particular option chain
for a specific trading day to compute
the implied volatility so for every
trading day we're looking forward to the
closest month and then getting the
closest strike we want to for at the
money options so we're going to retrieve
the Empire volatility for the one month
two month three month and four months
just as we've stated
so first thing we're going to do I need
to take in the root ticker I need this
function to take in the trading dates
the interval size and then the option
type
now the client I'm going to create the
client and I'm going to store all the
implied volatilities in this data's
dictionary that I will build up here I'm
defining my my essentially Columns of
data my keys that I'll use for this
dictionary the one month two month three
month and four month and then I'm going
to also can have a reference of the
total days so I can print out as I go
along now we're going to connect to the
data terminal I'm going to iterate
through every trade date and I'm going
to use enumerate so I can get the index
as well
so for every trade date the first thing
I want to do is get the expiry dates for
the specific contracts on those
particular trade dates so I'm
referencing those contracts to get the
indexes of those specific expiry dates
for a particular trade date we talked
about that before and then I'm just
going to apply that to our monthly
expirations to get that subsection of
those expiration dates once I've got
them for each expiry we want to get the
closest at the money IV so now we're
going to iterate through those four
expiration dates
we're going to determine the closest at
the money strike so the way we can do
that is we can iterate through all the
strikes of expiry date and then we're
going to then work out what the minimum
difference is between the underlying and
the strike and we're going to use that
strike so return the closest at the
money strike for that particular
Training Day
and that option so let's try and attempt
to get the historical options implied
volatility on that particular strike
with that particular expiration date and
the way you can do that is you require
the option requirement type dot implied
volatility all in cats there with a
underscore for that particular trading
day interval size and again I'm going to
take from the four uh for the 1400 so 2
o'clock in the afternoon
so here I'm then referencing I only want
the implied volatility data position
back but there are other things that
come back so yeah just be conscious read
through the docs of theta data so you
can see or equally just send a request
and return all of it so then you can
subsection the data yourself
so I'm then going to start store now I'm
going to store that data in the
dictionary so I've got for every trade
date I've got then the specific days to
expiry so either one month two month
three month or four month
and then if it's unavailable make it Nan
so I'm going to do that for every trade
date I'm going to make the request for
the API for both calls and puts and this
does take a while but the API is very
quick so I'm going to demonstrate it
right now so the problem is really that
we're doing it over 10 years of option
data which is incredible that we're
going historically we're looking forward
for a particular contract we're then
doing a call what was it at this
specific time on that trading day what
was the implied volatility which is kind
of mind-boggles me that we're able to do
that all with one API so to demonstrate
what this entity looks like let's just
run through a five day week of what that
looks like and let's time how quick that
is with the API so if I send the
response essentially I'm running through
the days first we need to connect to the
terminal and then once you've connected
to the terminal it's going to run
through really quickly so I'm doing the
requests for all my four expiries on
these particular dates and I'm run
through quite quickly so now I've done
the five days in 17.59 seconds and I've
got
um for each of those I've looked at the
specific contract of the closest had the
money for the one month two month three
month four month closest to those
trading dates and I've got the implied
volatility for 1400 every single day
based on the quote the level information
aggregated over that period of time on
that specific trading day quite
incredible
so now let's actually visualize this so
what have I done I've got all this data
I've got historical and I've got implied
volatility let's plot them together so
all I'm going to do is I'm going to
build up my data frame based on all that
information from 2012 and you'll notice
look I do have some missing data in some
places so let's just plot all that out
and see what data I have and the first
thing that you see when you see this
graph is you're probably going to notice
why is the red the green and the Orange
Line a little bit patchy before 2020 and
I asked myself the same reason oh is
there something wrong with the API or
something not happening here and then I
realized even though I had the
assumption that there should be quote
level data for at the money options on
Microsoft on these monthly options
series that hasn't been a requirement
since prior to 2000 2020 so I encourage
you to read the NASDAQ exchange rules in
detail and what you'll notice in Section
5 of Market maker quotations this actual
obligation and exchange rules was only
adopted in December 6
2019 and amended a few times since so
that's why when you look at this diagram
we've got quite patchy data
so the two-month three month and four
month out
options up until 2020 where then it
becomes very reliable but back here it's
like market makers were happy to offer
all those products and then there was
this period here between 2015 to 2020
where maybe it seems like it wasn't an
everyday occurrence on those monthlies
and now uh here it is now the
obligations are set out as in the rules
and they need to be actively traded by
the primary and the competitive market
makers ninety percent for the primary
and sixty percent of the time for the
competitive market makers on the options
and here we have a more liquid
transparent and open market so there you
go so what does that mean well
essentially I'm going to only take the
one month out the 30 day and we'll
compare that against our 30-day 2021
trading days spot volatility so let's
plot that and we can see now we have
this graph with our stock price in blue
and our implied volatility in green and
then the realized volatility in red now
you can see here that their their looks
there appears to be a very strong
correlation between the two and
obviously that shouldn't come as a
surprise to viewers on this channel but
if you don't know it's okay we're going
to go through it all in this implied
volatility series
so I encourage you looking at this graph
has what we plotted is this a fair
comparison is it a fair representation
just playing it day for day so the
implied volatility that I see on this
training day versus the rolling 30-day
realized volatility well essentially if
you believe that there's some kind of
autocorrelation or power in the
historical volatility or the implied
volatility to kind of forecast or or
have some information on the realized
volatility or you believe that
historical volatility is somehow
correlated to historical volatility in
the future so autocorrelation if you
believe this is the case then really
maybe we should consider Fair time scale
so remember the realized volatility is
backwards looking so it's over the time
periods T minus H goes to T whereas the
implied volatility is Ford's looking
over H time period so really at time T
right now that's actually the looking at
the period t plus h I'm remember H is
our 30 days or 21 trading days
so to compare this visually we could
shift the
realized volatility backwards by this H
period of time so we're going to shift
it by 21 days
backwards so let's shift our spot Vol by
21 days and you can see now that we have
the volatility listed at the beginning
of the period and then we don't have it
listed at the end of the period because
we don't know what they are yet
so
if I then plot that out you can see that
there seems to be a very strong
correlation with the realized volatility
and the implied volatility now we're
going to do further analysis on this in
the future but now you should just see
the correlation between these two uh two
volatilities yeah I mean it's pretty
implicit with with even just the eye and
observation but we're going to get into
the numbers and how you can actually
analyze this and what you do with that
information and how you can build up
models to forecast the volatility into
the future to hopefully give you some
kind of idea on the process of whether
implied volatility might be overpriced
or underpriced in the marketplace so
we're going to go into all of that in
more detail now one question that I want
to ask is is this data different for the
puts and should it be I pose you the
question if it should be different for a
particular strike at the money should
you have a different implied volatility
well I built up the implied volatility
again we see on the puts that we have
consistent data for the monthlies after
one month from 2020 when the rules
obviously got tighter on the exchange
thank you very much
and we've got patchy data beforehand so
if I then plot the one month puts versus
the one month calls we see very very
very strong correlation from a
particular point so maybe for the last
five years these look nearly identical
whereas before there were a little bit
more patchy and you can almost see that
the calls had consistently lower implied
volatility and then the implied
volatility that puts almost had higher
for a long period of time now my
question for you and we're going to
answer it in another video is
why is this why could this be and what
if and if there should be a difference
between implied volatility at the same
strike between calls and puts so I pose
that question to you we'd love to hear
your answer in the comments section
below